<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Derek&#39;s Hub</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Derek&#39;s Hub</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.139.0</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>PaperMod Contributors</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 15:18:31 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>New Python Features 3.10 - 3.14</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/new-features-py/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 15:18:31 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/new-features-py/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Starting from Python 3.10 released in Oct 2021 to Python 3.14 released last month, there are plenty of new features
added to the language that made it more intuitive to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to put a summary here to remind myself to make full use of the modern Pythonic idioms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;deferred-evaluation-of-annotation-314&#34;&gt;Deferred evaluation of annotation (3.14)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since Python 3 introduced type annotation, it is always evaluated immediately. In some cases, when we want to reference
the type that is not yet defined, we will have to do some trickery by quoting it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design Patterns in Python</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/design-pattern-py/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 19:00:53 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/design-pattern-py/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a super flexible language, Python is blazing fast to build working prototypes and get the steam going.
At the same time, it can also end up becoming a messy codebase and a pain to read later if being careless in the coding style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I would always prefer to look out for idiomatic patterns to keep the Python code maintainable and easy to work with (both for me and others).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bits and pieces of HTTP in Go</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/go-http/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 22:35:17 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/go-http/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The benefit of being a young programming language is that its design will incorporate the latest software engineering needs from the ground up.
Concepts like multi-thread processing, building RESTful API become the first class citizens in Go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, this is part of the motivation in designing Golang, as one of the authors commented about older programming languages in the keynote talk
&lt;a href=&#34;https://go.dev/talks/2012/splash.article&#34;&gt;Go at Google: Language Design in the Service of Software Engineering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A peek into Go Generics</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/go-generics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2024 21:39:17 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/go-generics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since version &lt;code&gt;1.18&lt;/code&gt;, Go has finally introduced the support for generics, together with &lt;code&gt;any&lt;/code&gt; as a type alias of &lt;code&gt;interface{}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gives more flexibility for user to create a general collection for similar data structures. Previously we have no choice but
to write up the same &lt;code&gt;struct&lt;/code&gt; for each data type we want to support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The syntax can look a bit strange if you are already used to the old-school Go code.
Or maybe it&amp;rsquo;s just because I haven&amp;rsquo;t used it often enough.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Structure in Go - Part 2</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/data-structure-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2023 15:02:58 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/data-structure-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is true that Go is designed with a minimalistic touch. It does not have a rich set of collections or in-built data structures like Java,
where you can just import &lt;code&gt;java.util.PriorityQueue&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;java.util.Stack&lt;/code&gt; and start using them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, besides the basic &lt;code&gt;map&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;slice&lt;/code&gt;, Go does come with a builtin &lt;code&gt;container&lt;/code&gt; package that we should at least be aware  and
make use of it to implement things like &lt;code&gt;Stack&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Queue&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;PriorityQueue&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Deque&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Structure in Go - Part 1</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/data-structure-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 20:28:17 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/data-structure-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;alias-type&#34;&gt;Alias type&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data structures start with the fundamental data types in Go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Numbers&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Boolean&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Array&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Struct&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Slice&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Pointer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the basic ones in Go, there are alias types that just provide more meaningful names for existing data types.
It&amp;rsquo;s good to be aware of them so as not to get confused when you happen to see them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Alias type&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Underlying type&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Why?&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;rune&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;int32&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;represent a Unicode character&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;byte&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;uint8&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;represent one byte (8 bits) of data&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;int&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;int32 / int64&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;adjusted for the system (32 bit / 64 bit)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also define custom alias type:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Common Go channel uses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/go-channel/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 11:17:04 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/go-channel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Go is known for its native support for concurrency. You can easily spin up a concurrent execution (i.e. goroutine) using keyword &lt;code&gt;go&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is similar to OS thread but managed by Go runtime scheduler instead of OS kernel. The underlying implementation actually employs an M:N model to multiplex M goroutines onto N threads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the great power of concurrency comes with the responsibility to handle synchronisation in the right manner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Built-in functions in Go</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/go-built-in/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2023 11:17:04 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/go-built-in/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The builtins are functions in Golang that you can call directly &lt;em&gt;without having to import any package&lt;/em&gt;; they just come with the programming language itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full list resides in the builtin standard library: &lt;code&gt;https://pkg.go.dev/builtin&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the builtin functions are widely used, so it&amp;rsquo;s important to know them by heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motivation for this post comes from the fact that &lt;code&gt;Go 1.21.0&lt;/code&gt; has introduced multiple new handy builtins (which doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen frequently).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>YouTube channels I like for learning French</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/learning-french/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2023 12:17:04 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/learning-french/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my third year at university, I got the chance to experience the French part of Switzerland for a semester through an exchange program
at Ecole Polytechnique Federale de Lausanne (EPFL).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought knowing a bit of the language would definitely boost my experience there, so I decided to take a French module at my home university.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I ended up loving it. There are a few channels that really helped me out with daily conversations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>YouTube channels I like for learning German</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/learning-german/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2023 12:17:04 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/learning-german/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I took German as my first elective module back in my first year of university.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I found it is a great opportunity to connect with people outside my faculty and from completely different cultural background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And obviously I get to learn about German culture as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I&amp;rsquo;m a practical person. I believe YouTube is a great place to get exposure to daily vocabulary, different accents and simply a real touch to local people.
So here are some great channels that I enjoy immensely while learning the language.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
