<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Derek&#39;s Hub</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Derek&#39;s Hub</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.139.0</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>PaperMod Contributors</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 20:28:17 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Data Structure in Go - Part 1</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/data-structure-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 20:28:17 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/data-structure-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;alias-type&#34;&gt;Alias type&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data structures start with the fundamental data types in Go:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Numbers&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Boolean&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Array&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Struct&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Slice&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Pointer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the basic ones in Go, there are alias types that just provide more meaningful names for existing data types.
It&amp;rsquo;s good to be aware of them so as not to get confused when you happen to see them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Alias type&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Underlying type&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Why?&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;rune&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;int32&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;represent a Unicode character&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;byte&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;uint8&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;represent one byte (8 bits) of data&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;int&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;int32 / int64&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;adjusted for the system (32 bit / 64 bit)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also define custom alias type:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Common Go channel uses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/go-channel/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 11:17:04 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/go-channel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Go is known for its native support for concurrency. You can easily spin up a concurrent execution (i.e. goroutine) using keyword &lt;code&gt;go&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is similar to OS thread but managed by Go runtime scheduler instead of OS kernel. The underlying implementation actually employs an M:N model to multiplex M goroutines onto N threads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the great power of concurrency comes with the responsibility to handle synchronisation in the right manner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Built-in functions in Go</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/go-built-in/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2023 11:17:04 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/go-built-in/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The builtins are functions in Golang that you can call directly &lt;em&gt;without having to import any package&lt;/em&gt;; they just come with the programming language itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full list resides in the builtin standard library: &lt;code&gt;https://pkg.go.dev/builtin&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the builtin functions are widely used, so it&amp;rsquo;s important to know them by heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motivation for this post comes from the fact that &lt;code&gt;Go 1.21.0&lt;/code&gt; has introduced multiple new handy builtins (which doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen frequently).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>YouTube channels I like for learning French</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/learning-french/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2023 12:17:04 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/learning-french/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my third year at university, I got the chance to experience the French part of Switzerland for a semester through an exchange program
at Ecole Polytechnique Federale de Lausanne (EPFL).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought knowing a bit of the language would definitely boost my experience there, so I decided to take a French module at my home university.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I ended up loving it. There are a few channels that really helped me out with daily conversations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>YouTube channels I like for learning German</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/learning-german/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2023 12:17:04 +0800</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/learning-german/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I took German as my first elective module back in my first year of university.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I found it is a great opportunity to connect with people outside my faculty and from completely different cultural background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And obviously I get to learn about German culture as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I&amp;rsquo;m a practical person. I believe YouTube is a great place to get exposure to daily vocabulary, different accents and simply a real touch to local people.
So here are some great channels that I enjoy immensely while learning the language.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
